Impossible burgers have been criticized
for containing heme iron.
What does that mean
for consumers’ health?
Check out the video.
"Heme Iron in Impossible Burgers and Cancer Risk"
In an editorial in the Journal of
the American Medical Association,
the chair of nutrition at
Harvard pointed out that many
plant-based meat alternatives,
such as Beyond Meat and
the Impossible Burger,
can be high in sodium.
But an issue specific to the Impossible
Burger was the heme they add, derived
from soybean plants to enhance the
product's meaty flavor and appearance.
Safety analyses have failed to find any
toxicity risk specific to the soy heme
they have yeast churn out.
The FDA has agreed both
for use as a flavor and
color enhancer: safe.
In other words, just as safe as the heme
found in blood and muscle in meat.
But how much is that really saying?
The concern raised in the op-ed, for
example, was that higher intake of heme
has been associated with an elevated
risk of developing type 2 diabetes.
But not just diabetes, killer #7 in
the United States, higher dietary
intake of heme iron
is associated
with an increased risk of
cardiovascular disease as well,
killers #1, 4 and 13: heart disease,
stroke, and high blood pressure.
But since heme is found
mostly in meat,
heme intake may just
be a marker for meat intake.
It's like with diabetes: three
meta-analyses published to date,
and they all reported the same link.
But there's lots of reasons why
meat may increase diabetes risk,
like advanced glycation end products,
produced when animal products
are baked, broiled, grilled,
fried, or barbequed.
So how do we know that the heme
isn't just some innocent bystander?
The same issue arises about
the link between heme intake
and increased breast cancer risk.
Since heme iron is coming from
animal foods, it could be any
of the other meat components,
like animal fat or meat mutagens,
compounds in meat that
can cause DNA mutations.
And hey, what about all the hormonal
steroids implanted into cattle
that may play a role in the
development of breast cancer?
A study in Japan found that
beef imported from the United States
contained up to 600 times the
levels of estrogens like estradiol.
US beef.
Japanese beef.
And higher consumption of estrogen-rich
beef due to hormone implantation
may facilitate estrogen
accumulation in the human body
and thus affecting women's
risk for breast cancer.
So yeah, heme iron intake was
associated with breast cancer risk,
but maybe that's just because the heme
and the hormones are traveling together
in the same package: meat.
This is about as good as any
observational study can do.
The NIH-AARP study is the largest
prospective study on diet and health
ever, following more than a half million
men and women for over a decade now.
With such a huge dataset they
could take advantage of the fact that
different meats have different amounts
of heme, so they could try to tease out
the heme components by, in effect,
comparing people eating different
amounts of heme, but the
same amount of meat
to see if heme is independently
associated with disease.
And indeed, that's what they showed:
an independent association not only
from nitrites in processed meat, but heme
and mortality from almost all causes:
death from diabetes, heart disease,
stroke, respiratory disease,
kidney disease, liver disease,
cancer, and all causes put together.
They calculated that about
one-fifth of the association between
like eating burgers and the
shortening of your lifespan
could be statistically accounted
for by just the heme itself,
but that's assuming cause-and-effect.
Even an independent association
is still an association. You can't
prove cause and effect until you put it
to the test in interventional studies.
Normally, we don't necessarily
care about the mechanism.
When the World Health Organization
designated bacon, ham, hot dogs,
luncheon meat, sausage
to be Group 1 carcinogens,
meaning we know these products
cause cancer in human beings,
who cares if it's the heme iron, or
the heterocyclic aromatic amines,
or the polycyclic aromatic
hydrocarbons, or the N-nitrosamines.
They're all wrapped up in the
same place, processed meat,
which we know causes cancer.
So we should just try to stay away
from it, regardless of the mechanism.
But with the advent of the Impossible
Burger, we really do have to know,
because for the first time we have
lots of heme without any actual meat.
So we need to know if
the heme itself is harmful.
For that, we'll have to turn
to interventional studies,
which we'll cover next.
In muscle meat there’s a
heme protein that contributes
to the meaty taste of meat.
Well, there’s a heme protein in
the roots of soybean plants too
that can be churned out to
provide a similar flavor and aroma
in plant-based meat,
which is used to make
the Impossible Burger possible.
The question is: are
there any downsides?
When the European Food Safety
Authority was considering
the safety of adding heme iron
to foods, their main concern
was a potential increased
risk of colon cancer.
We know meat causes cancer.
Processed meat—bacon, ham, hot dogs,
lunch meat, and sausage—
is considered a Group 1
carcinogen, meaning we know
it causes cancer in people,
with the same level of certainty
that something like
smoking causes cancer.
Whereas something like
a burger, just probably
causes cancer in
people, kind of like DDT.
But what’s the role of heme iron?
I mean, there are all
sorts of potential mechanisms
to explain the cancer risk.
Meat’s got the pro-inflammatory
long-chain omega-6
arachidonic acid, more of the
aging- and cancer-associated
methionine, trans fat,
endogenous hormones like IGF-1,
not to mention the ones
that are implanted in animals
as hormonal growth-promoters.
Then there are all the
toxic pollutants that build up
the food chain, like pesticides—
I didn’t even know
about the formaldehyde.
According to the prestigious IARC,
the International Agency
for Research on Cancer,
there is strong evidence that
heterocyclic aromatic amines
contribute to the
cancer-causing mechanism.
These DNA-damaging compounds
are formed when muscle tissue
is exposed to high, dry heat –
grilling, roasting, baking, broiling_
basically anything above
steaming or stewing.
There is also strong evidence
that the formation of so-called
N-nitroso compounds contribute
to the cancer-causing mechanism.
These are carcinogens that
can form inside our gut
when we eat the meat.
But there is also strong evidence,
according to the IARC,
that heme iron contributes
to the cancer-causing mechanism.
Normally, I might leave it there,
but other authoritative bodies
I respect, like the American
Institute for Cancer Research
and the World Cancer Research
Fund, are more tentative.
While they agree there is some
evidence that the consumption
of foods containing heme iron
might increase the risk
of colorectal cancer,
they consider the evidence
suggesting such a
connection to be limited.
Much of the available evidence is
based on lab animal data
such as this: in which
dietary heme was found
to disrupt the gut flora,
aggravate inflammation,
and potentiate the development
of intestinal tumors in mice.
But it’s critical to note
that in all the laboratory
animal models that
have been used,
the rodents ingested
meat or heme equivalent
to people eating up to
40,000 pounds of meat a day.
Even the smallest
dose would be like
a dozen Impossible Burgers a day.
It’s easy to see how casual
readers could get confused, though.
In this study, ascribing a
central role for heme iron
in the colon cancer
development associated with meat,
the authors claimed they
were aimed at determining
at nutritional doses, which
was the main factor involved
in cancer promotion. So,
doses of heme were chosen
to mimic red meat
consumption and… Boom!
Significant increase in tumor load.
The researchers conclude
that their findings
strongly “suggest that at
concentrations that are in line
with human meat consumption,
heme iron is associated
with the promotion of
colon [cancer development].”
But if you look at the
actual diet they were given
and do the math, that’s
500 times the level of heme
found in people’s diets, in excess of
like 70 pounds of meat a day.
Of course, even if they
really did use the right doses
they’re still going to end up
with data on the wrong species,
which brings us to clinical
studies which we’ll explore next.